Finding Aid for Cordelia Creswell papers, 1886-1935 and 1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cordelia Creswell papers 1886-1935 and 1950
Creswell, Cordelia, 1868?-1950.
1.5 linear feet
851053 Aa 2
Special education coordinator in Grand Rapids, Michigan. Budgets, payrolls, annual and individual reports on students, program, delinquency, and education for the retarded.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Charles Rawley ( 1991 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Cordelia Creswell was supervisor of special education for the Grand Rapids public schools. She was a pioneer in organizing special classes in speech correction, sight saving and orthopedic work. Her teaching career began in 1888 after graduation from Grand Rapids High school. She taught school for a few years, then left to raise a family. She resumed her career in 1903. In 1910 she was made principal of the auxiliary school in Grand Rapids. In 1910, she became supervisor for the board of education of all special classes, a position she held until her retirement in 1932.
The Cordelia Creswell collection includes correspondence, budgets, payrolls, annual and individual reports on students, program, delinquency, and education for the retarded.
Subjects:
Education--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Juvenile delinquency--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; People with mental disabilities--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Teachers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women teachers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.
Contributors:
Creswell, Margaret.
- Correspondence, 1886-1932
  - 1886-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927 (Box 1)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Special education, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Survey of special classes, 1921-1931 (Box 1)
  - Social Workers Conference, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Reports: special education for the mentally retarded
    - 1914-1916 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931 and undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1)
  - School finances miscellanea, 1926-1930 (Box 1)
  - Test result miscellanea, undated (Box 1)
- Other papers, 1896-1935, 1950
  - 1896-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 2)
  - Undated, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Obituary notice, 1950 (Box 2)